Finding Aid for J. David Singer papers, 1947-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
J. David Singer papers 1947-2009 1957-2000
Singer, J. David (Joel David), 1925-
861057 Aa 2
University of Michigan professor of political science, research scientist at the Mental Health Research Institute, and pioneer in the interdisciplinary and quantitative approach to conflict resolution. Administrative papers of Center for Research on Conflict Resolution, Correlates of War Project, and the Journal of Conflict Resolution, topical files on numerous organizations and subjects, and research papers from disarmament negotiations study.
21.3 linear feet in 23 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library in several accessions beginning in 1985 by J. David Singer (Donor no. 7207 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
A widely recognized authority in the field of peace research, J. David Singer has been associated with the Political Science Department and the Mental Health Research Institute of the University of Michigan since the late 1950s. Noting the various facets of his career, he has written that "as a researcher, teacher, consultant and activist, my goal has been to bring rigorous scientific methods to bear on the cause of war question, and to encourage the integration of ethical concern and hard evidence."
Born in Brooklyn, New York in 1925, J. David Singer received his B.A. from Duke University in 1946 and his Ph.D. from New York University in 1956. After serving as an instructor at N.Y.U. and Vassar College and as a visiting fellow in social relations at Harvard University, he came to the University of Michigan as a visiting assistant professor in political science in 1958. He became a senior scientist at the Mental Health Research Institute in 1960 and since 1965 he has also been a professor in the Political Science Department, becoming a Professor Emeritus in 2002. Singer served in the United States Navy as a deck officer at the end of World War II and during the Korean War. He has also worked as a consultant for the United States Department of State, U.S. Department of the Navy, U.S. Foreign Service Institute, Bendix Systems Division, and others.
Singer was a member of Ann Arbor's Center for Research on Conflict Resolution, which formed in the mid-1950s. Organized by several prominent University of Michigan social scientists including Robert Angell (sociology), Kenneth Boulding (economics), and Daniel Katz (psychology), the center was an outgrowth of the Journal of Conflict Resolution founded in 1957 to encourage more vigorous research into the problems of achieving international peace. Faculty members associated with the center undertook research into such topics as military policy, arms control and disarmament. In 1963, Singer and the Mental Health Research Institute received a Carnegie grant to "review all international crises since the Napoleonic Wars with the aim of discriminating situations which were resolved in open wars and those which were settled by other means." One product of this research project, (later known as the Correlates of War Project or simply the COW Project), was a large computer data base containing information on past international conflicts as well as on certain economic and political variables which might explain the fluctuating nature of warfare. Over the years, J. David Singer authored a number of major studies (many using data produced by the COW Project) including: Deterrence, Arms Control and Disarmament: Toward a Synthesis in National Security Policy (1962, with Melvin Small); The Wages of War, 1816-1965: A Statistical Handbook (1972, with Susan Jones); Beyond Conjecture in International Politics: Abstracts of Data Based Research (1972, with Dorothy L. Barr); and Resort to Arms: International and Civil War, 1816-1980 (1982). In 1971, the Center for Research on Conflict Resolution was closed. However, the COW Project continued into the 21st Century with funding from various outside sources.
As professor of political science, J. David Singer has been a consistent advocate of rigorous training in scientific research methods. While acknowledging the value of some types of "pre-scientific" political science, he has urged that graduate courses and faculty recruitment reflect the new needs for statistical analysis, computer literacy, and reproducible research in political science. As coordinator of the World Politics field within the department (1969-1975), he pressed for such scientific rigor especially in the field of international relations. During the 1980s, Singer criticized the general decline in funding for higher education and what he felt to be the dilution of the political science program at the University of Michigan. In addition to his teaching duties in Ann Arbor, Singer has frequently been a visiting professor in Europe. He also participated in many conferences at various international peace institutes in Europe and Asia.
As a peace activist, Singer has been a prominent speaker at a wide range of public forums and rallies. A critic of narrow nationalist interests in international politics, he has advocated arms reduction as a necessary first step toward world peace. As a member of the Union of Concerned Scientists, SANE, and the World Federalist Association he has urged restraint in international conflict through petitions and political endorsements. He also publicly criticized United States government policy on such issues as the bombing of Cambodia in the 1960s and that of Libya in the 1980s.
Besides his role as researcher, teacher, and peace activist, Singer has maintained an interest in certain features of campus life at the University of Michigan. As a bike and motorcycle commuter he sought to improve motorcycle parking at the university as his many letters to the parking operations office will testify. He also took a special interest in the recreational sports program (especially tennis). Other concerns ranging from the quality of programming on the university radio station (WUOM) to the level of noise on the "diag" produced a number of lively letters in the 1960s and 1970s.
J. David Singer died in Ann Arbor in December 2009.
The J. David Singer papers document the career of a leading political science researcher, teacher, and peace activist. The bulk of the materials span the 1950s to the year 2000 and are arranged into nine distinct series:
Biographical Materials
Topical Files
Correspondence
Lectures and Conferences
Publications
Grant Proposals
Teaching
Programs
Later materials
Audio-Visual Materials
Subjects:
Citizens Exchange Corps.; Conflict management.; Disarmament.; International law.; Journal of conflict resolution.; Singer, J. David (Joel David), 1925-2009; United World Federalists (U.S.); University of Michigan. Center for Research on Conflict Resolution.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical material
  The Biographical Materials series, .5 linear feet, contains clippings, press releases, biographical statements, curriculum vitae, photographs, and general information concerning the personal and professional career of J. David Singer. Interesting items include a file concerning Professor Singer's loss of his United States security clearance, copies of his "Red Squad" police surveillance files, and a 1981 appearance before the United States Congress.
  - Assorted Biographies (Box 1)
  - Congressional Appearance 1981 (Box 1)
  - Consulting, United States Air Force 1965, MITRE Corporation, 1967, Bendix, 1965-1966, Stanford Research Inc., 1966, and others (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
  - "In Praise of David Singer" (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Professional Activities Questionnaires 1985-2001 (Box 1)
  - Red Squad Michigan State Police File (Box 1)
  - Security Clearance, Federal Government (includes FOIA requests) (Box 1)
  - "The Singer Curve," 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Singer Festschrift (Box 1)
  - Transcription of Court Testimony 1986 (Box 1)
  - United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, Department of State 1967-1972 (Box 1)
- Topical Files circa 1940-2000
  The Topical File series, approximately 4.5 linear feet, is arranged alphabetically by topic and evidences all facets of Singer's work from the 1940s through the present. Researchers interested in Singer's early association with the Journal of Conflict Resolution and the Center for Conflict Resolution should consult files under those folder headings as well as "Correspondence, general" for the relevant years. Those interested in more general trends in political science research and Singer's appraisals of those trends should consult "Evaluations of Proposals/Manuscripts, 1966-1999", "Research Proposals, 1961-1983", and of "Editorial Board Assignments, 1985-1993."
  J. David Singer has spent over thirty years as a political science teacher at the University of Michigan and many portions of the collection pertain to that role. Singer took a keen interest in graduate education in political science generally and the world politics field specifically and folders under "Political Science Department" evidence the evolution of political science education from 1960. For those interested in Singer's views on the impact of budget cuts at the University of Michigan in the early 1980s and on the new priorities in political science research during the Reagan administration, the researcher would do well to consult the general correspondence files for those years.
  The folders "Political endorsements and petitions signed" relate most directly to Singer's role as a peace activist. These folders contain letters written on behalf of anti-war causes from the 1960s to the present. Singer's early involvement in the peace movement can be gleaned from the folders "United World Federalists, 1947-1950." It should be noted that Singer was a popular speaker at many academic and non-academic gatherings both in the United States and abroad. Topics ranged broadly from theoretical problems in peace research to contemporary foreign policy issues. Also of particular note are those file folders containing material on international peace associations and Singer's participation in these professional organizations. Hence, researchers interested in peace activism as well as those interested in peace research may want to consult the folders "Conferences and lectures, 1960-1989."
  Finally, those interested in campus life in Ann Arbor (especially during the 1960s and 1970s) should consult "University of Michigan Administration." These folders contain correspondence between Singer and various university administrators regarding topics of special interest to Singer on the University of Michigan campus.
  - Americans For SALT 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - American Political Science Association 1969-1982 (Box 1)
  - Applications of Social Science and History (Box 1)
  - Appeasement (Box 1)
  - Berner Program in Peace Research and Education (Box 1)
  - Center for Research on Conflict Resolution
    - Correspondence, memoranda and research proposals 1959-1962, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, memoranda and research proposals 1963-1972, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Undated materials (Box 2)
  - Citizens Exchange Corps
    - Correspondence 1962-1982 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Newsletters and clippings (Box 2)
  - China-Taiwan Rivalry (Box 2)
  - China-USSR Disputes (Box 2)
  - Citizen's Exchange Corps
    - Correspondence 1962-1982 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Newsletters and Clippings (Box 2)
  - Committee for National Security 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - Computer Research, MIT and the United States Department of State, Advanced Research Projects Agency 1967-1981 (Box 2)
  - Decision-Making in Conflict, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Disarmament Negotiations Study 1957-1960
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Papers (Box 2)
  - Economics of War (Box 2)
  - Editorial Board Assignments 1985-1993 (Box 2)
  - Europe May-June, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Experimental Design (Box 2)
  - Federation of American Scientists 1991-1995 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Policy and Effective Citizens (Box 3)
  - Franco-German Rivalry (Box 3)
  - Gradualist Way to Peace, Ann Arbor Council 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Imperialism Models (Box 3)
  - Intelligence (Box 3)
  - International Ethics, Quincy Wright 1981-1993 (Box 3)
  - International Political Science Association Research Committee on Peace and Conflict (Box 3)
  - International Society for Research on Aggression
    - General (Box 3)
    - Printed Material (Box 3)
  - International Studies Association
    - 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
    - Committee Lists (Box 3)
    - Foreign Associations (Box 3)
    - Foreign Visits (Box 3)
    - India (Box 3)
    - Middle East (Box 3)
    - Future World Assemblies (Box 3)
    - Karl W. Deutsch Award (Box 3)
    - Professional Rights and Responsibilities Committee (Box 3)
    - Singer presidency (Box 3)
  - Journal of Conflict Resolution
    - Correspondence and board meeting minutes 1959-1982, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - Move to Yale University 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Undated material (Box 4)
  - Klingberg, Frank L., Expert Consultant, Office of the Secretary of War, "Historical Study of War Casualties" manuscript and "Predicting the Termination of War: Battle Casualties and Population Losses," 1945 (Box 4)
  - Level of Aggression and Analysis (Box 4)
  - Mid-East Treaties (Box 4)
  - Military Capabilities, Allocations (Box 4)
  - Military Expenditures (Box 4)
  - Military Preparation, Pathology (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1958-1991 (Box 4)
  - Mobility and Fluidity Data 1970 (Box 4)
  - "National Integrity: The Persistence of Sovereignty and Nationalism," Henry Barbera circa 1985 (Box 4)
  - National Research Council on Peace Strategy, Correspondence 1962-1974 (Box 4)
  - Non-violence (Box 4)
  - Nuclear Weapons (Box 4)
    (incl. declassified documents)
  - Peace Institutes
    - Berlin Science Center, International Institute for Conflict and Peace Research 1970-1976 (Box 4)
    - Institute for Peace and Conflict Research (Denmark) 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - International Peace Research Institute (Oslo) 1963-1981 (Box 4)
    - Peace Science Society 1968-1989 (Box 4)
    - Stockholm International Peace Research Institute 1966-1971 (Box 4)
  - Peace Science Society 1991-2003 (Box 4)
  - Policy Applications of Social Sciences, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Political Endorsements and Petitions Signed 1962-1994, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Political Science Department
    - Faculty Appointments and Tenure Decisions 1964-1982 (Box 5)
    - Faculty list 1910-1976 (Box 5)
    - Graduate program 1967-1976, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Institute of Public Policy Studies (Box 5)
    - Language Requirements (Esperanto) (Box 5)
    - Master in World Affairs, Proposal (Box 5)
    - Recommendations For Colleagues 1994-1999, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Teaching Assistants Memoranda (Box 5)
    - World Politics Program
      - Curriculum 1967-1984, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Graduate Level, Part Time Study (Box 5)
      - Memoranda 1970-1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1966-1969 (Box 5)
      - Personnel 1965-1983 (Box 22)
      - Research Club (Box 5)
  - Russia-Japan Rivalry (Box 5)
  - Science and Pseudo-Science (Box 5)
  - Social Science and Foreign Affairs 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - "The Societal Aspects of Disarmament," 1978 (United Nations Colloquium) (Box 5)
  - Social Science Education (Box 5)
  - Suicide, Homicide (Box 5)
  - Taipei November 6-9, 1999 (Box 5)
  - United Nations, Strengthening the Secretary General 1984-1995 (Box 5)
  - United Nations University 1973-1978 (Box 5)
  - United World Federalists 1947-1950, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - University Committee on the Problems of War and Peace 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan Administration
    - General 1965-1982, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Parking operations 1962-1973 (Box 6)
    - Sports activities 1966-1976 (Box 6)
  - USIA Tour, Europe (Box 6)
  - Vienna November 1999 (Box 6)
  - Vienna Sabbatical 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - War Control Planners Inc. 1971-1980 (Box 6)
  - War Data Articles 1996-2001 (Box 6)
  - Weiss, Herbert K., War Distributions 1966-1991 (Box 6)
  - World Peace Tax Fund 1974-1980 (Box 6)
  - World Without War Council 1977-1981 (Box 6)
- Correspondence 1978-2000
  The Correspondence Series (1978-2000), approximately 6.75 linear feet, is arranged chronologically and topically into two subseries. It consists of incoming and outgoing letters written primarily between Singer and his professional colleagues. Also included are letters to friends, the media, prominent political figures, and various presidents of the University of Michigan. In addition, there is one separate file folder of correspondence between Singer and the economist Kenneth Boulding and his wife Elise.
  Materials in this series provide information on Singer's job search as a young Ph.D. graduate, and a wealth of information on his thoughts on political science, war research, and other societal concerns (found in the "Letters to the Editor" and "Policy Makers" folders). Other items, such as the MacArthur Foundation file and the "Dis-satisfaction" folder, shed light on some of the professional controversies that occurred during Singer's career.
  - Chronological
    - 1947-1975, 15 folders (Box 6)
    - 1976-1990, 17 folders (Box 7)
    - 1990-June, 1998, 26 folders (Box 8)
    - July, 1998-2000, 37 folders (Box 9)
    - 2001-2004, 29 folders (Box 10)
    - 2005-2007 (Box 11)
  - Topical Correspondence
    - Boulding-Singer Correspondence 1990-1992 (Box 11)
    - Chinese Translations 1990-1992, 1999 (Box 11)
    - The Congress of Scientists on Survival, New York City 1963 (Box 11)
    - "Dis-Satisfaction," 1982-1997 (Box 11)
    - Elected Officials (Political Issues) 1962-1989 (Box 11)
    - Inter-University Consortium for Political Research, incl. International Archive 1967-1971 (Box 11)
    - Job Search 1995 (Box 11)
    - Russell Leng 1971-1975 (Box 11)
    - Letters to Editor 1951-1993, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - MacArthur Foundation Grant 1984 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Hana Pakorna Case (Box 11)
    - Policy Makers 1950-1978, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Publishers 1965-1976, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - James Lee Ray 1974-1981 (Box 12)
    - Reports from Assistants 1964-1970 (Box 12)
    - Gerald Schneider-Ohio June, 1995 (Box 12)
    - Melvin Small and Vilma 1964-1970 (Box 12)
    - William Thompson, War Anthology 1983-1984 (Box 12)
    - U.S. Arms Control and Disarmament Agency 1971 (Box 12)
- Lectures and Conferences 1960-1996
  The Lectures and Conferences series (1960-1996), approximately .75 linear feet, contains information regarding lectures given by Singer and conferences in which he participated. There are a few speech transcripts included, but much of the materials provide only background information. Also included in this series is background information on his lecture tours of the Western United States, Europe and Asia from 1977 to 1978.
  - Correspondence 1960-1989, 13 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 13)
  - American Political Science Association-Chicago August 13-September 3, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Carter Center Conference August 28-29, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Gronigan/Amsterdam September, 1995 (Box 13)
  - "History of War Research," 1978 (Box 13)
  - Import of Military Spending (Box 13)
  - "Interdisciplinary Research: A Social Science Perspective," January 21, 1993 (Box 13)
  - International Studies Association 1995-1996 (Box 13)
  - Israel May 27-30, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Lecture Tours
    - Asia 1978 (Box 13)
    - Europe 1977 (Box 13)
    - Western United States 1977 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Public Appearances, Speeches (includes transcript) (Box 13)
  - Norway June, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Peace Research Institute Office (Box 13)
  - Peace Science-Columbus October 13-15, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Rolling Chair, Gronigan (Box 13)
  - Sweden June 5-13, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Symposium on Armament, Tension, & War September 1977 (Box 13)
  - Vienna November 15-23, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Uppsala November 17-21, 1993 (Box 13)
  - "The U.S. Foreign and Military Policies in the 1980s" 1978 (Box 13)
- Publications 1957-2007
  The Publications series, approximately 2.5 linear feet, contains over 250 items in the chronological Articles and Manuscripts subseries, spanning the duration of J. David Singer's career. A selected number of articles also contain their accompanying research files, and are organized by the name of article. Additional notable items include a 1992 "Armed Rivalry in the Middle East" unit for High School Students and a report titled: "Soviet and American Foreign Policy Attitudes: A Content Analysis of Elite Articulations," prepared for the United States Naval Ordnance Test Station in 1964
  - Articles and Manuscripts
    - 1953-1959 9 items (Box 13)
    - 1960s, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - 1970s, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1970s (cont.), 4 folders (Box 14)
    - 1980s, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - 1990s, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 2000-2007, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Abstracts 1963-1988 (Box 15)
  - "Armed Rivalry in the Middle East: A Unit for High School Students," 1992 (Box 15)
  - "Beyond Conjecture in International Politics" (Box 15)
  - Book Reviews (Box 15)
  - Book Reviews and Publisher Ephemera (Box 15)
  - "The Correlates of War I & II" (Box 15)
  - "Cumulative Papers in International Research" (Box 15)
  - "Deterrence, Arms Control, and Disarmament" (Box 15)
  - "Explaining War: Selected Papers from the Correlates of War Project" (Box 15)
  - "Financing International Organization" (Box 15)
  - "Forewords and Prefaces" (Box 15)
  - "Human Behavior and International Politics" (Box 15)
  - "International War: An Anthology" (Box 15)
  - "Measuring the Correlates of War" (Box 15)
  - "Models, Methods, and Progress in World Politics: A Peace Research Odyssey" (Box 15)
  - "Orbis" (Box 15)
  - "The Political Origins of International War: A Multifactorial Review" (Box 15)
  - "Quantitative Indicators in World Politics" (Box 15)
  - "Quantitative International Politics" (Box 15)
  - "Resort to Arms: International and Civil Wars, 1816-1980" (Box 15)
  - "The Study of International Politics" (Box 15)
  - "To Augur Well: Early Warning Indicators in World Politics" (Box 15)
  - Translations, French (Quebec) 1984, German, 1974, Italian, 1965, and Swedish, 1985 (Box 15)
  - Translations, German; Italian; Japanese; and Korean (Box 15)
  - United States Naval Ordnance Test Station, "Soviet and American Foreign Policy Attitudes: A Content Analysis of Elite Articulations," 1964 (Box 15)
- Grant Proposals 1958-1997
  The Grant Proposal Series (1958-1981), approximately 2 linear feet, contains files on Singer's involvement in actively obtaining funding from various foundations in order to continue his research in the area of peace and conflict studies, including the Ford Foundation and the National Science Foundation.
  - ABE Proposal (United States -- Japan) 1992 (Box 16)
  - Berlin Project 1979-1981 (Box 16)
  - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching 1994 (Box 16)
  - Ford Foundation
    - 1975-1977 (Box 16)
    - 1978 (Box 16)
    - 1980 (Box 16)
  - Funding Proposals and Correspondence 1986-1997 (Box 16)
  - Funding Proposals, Funded 1989, 1992 (Box 16)
  - Funding Proposals, Un-funded 1975-1997, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Guggenheim Foundation 1978 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous Proposals and Evaluations (Box 16)
  - National Science Foundation
    - 1967-1969 (Box 16)